Robert E. Lee Papers WLU.Coll.0064
Washington and Lee University, University Library Special Collections and Archives
- Letters to and about Robert E. Lee, 1837-1870 (Box 7-12A)
  - Letters to and about Robert E. Lee, 1866-02-01-1866-05-31 (Box 7A, Folder 36-63)
    - Correspondences, 1866-02-27-1866-02-28 (Box 7A, Folder 42)
      - Cordes Sisters to Robert E. Lee, 1866-02-27; Cordes, Theodora; Cordes, Amelia; Byrnes, Mary; Cordes, Theodore, Captain; Cordes Family; Wittecher, Louisa (Box 7A, Folder 42)
        This letter was written by the Cordes Sisters and their personal friend Mary Byrnes from Ridgevill, South Carolina on February 27, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. The letter was sent in care of the sisters' father, Captain Theodore Cordes from Charleston, South Carolina. The letter is a follow up to a previous request of the sisters that went unanswered from December of 1865. The sisters requested some small memento from Lee, as they had great respect for him.
        South Carolina -- Charleston; South Carolina -- Ridgeville; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward)
      - Maria G. Slaughter to Robert E. Lee, 1866-02-27; Slaughter, Mary G. (Box 7A, Folder 42)
        This letter was written by Mary G. Slaughter on February 27, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Slaughter writes to introduce Stark Arnold to Lee as the nephew of Stonewall Jackson. She vouches for his integrity and explains his situation of desiring an education without direct means. She requests that Lee assist him in gaining an education.
        Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Jackson family; Arnold, Stark William, Rev; Jackson, Thomas Jonathan (Stonewall)
      - George W. Leyburn to Robert E. Lee, 1866-02-27; Leyburn, George W.; Leyburn family (Box 7A, Folder 42)
        This letter was written by G. W. Leyburn from Big Lick, Virginia on February 27, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. In the letter, Leyburn makes reference to a previous conversation he and Lee had regarding the nature of education. He expands on this topic and asks a series of questions regarding education in the South and requests a written response to the questions. He explains that he wishes to have Lee's stance while Leyburn acts to acquire subscriptions for Washington College's endowment.
    - Correspondences, 1866-03-01-1866-03-03 (Box 7A, Folder 43)
      - M. B. Smith to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-01; Smith, M. B., Mrs. (Box 7A, Folder 43)
        This letter was written by Mrs. M. B. Smith from Port Royal, Virginia on March 1, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Smith informs Lee that she wishes for her son to attend Washington College. She requests Lee for a school catalogue.
      - J. M. Handely to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-01; Handely, J. M. (Box 7A, Folder 43)
        This letter was written by J. M. Handely on March 1, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. In the letter, Handely requests a copy of Lee's ongoing work on the history of the "Great Rebellion."
      - Edward A. Pollard to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-02; Pollard, Edward A. (Box 7A, Folder 43)
        This letter and attached news clippings were written by Edward A. Pollard from Norfolk, Virginia on March 2, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. In the letter, Pollard explains, in reference to a previous correspondence, that he has become aware of an individual who has published his own scholarly work on the Civil War called "The Lost Cause" in the newspaper The New York News and is seeking action. He sent the letter attached with two clippings from papers in which Pollard directly addresses the culprit and publicly denounces his actions of infringement.
      - Great Southern & Western Accident & Life Insurance Co. to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-02; Great Southern & Western Accident & Life Insurance Co. (Box 7A, Folder 43)
        This letter was written on behalf of the Great Southern & Western Accident & Life Insurace Company of New Orleans, Louisiana on March 2, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. The company writes to inform Lee that he has been elected one of five members of the Non-Resident Board of stockholders.
      - W. S. Neal to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-03; Neal, W. S. (Box 7A, Folder 43)
        This letter was written by W. S. Neal on behalf of the Jefferson Davis Society of the Stonewall Institute from Perry County, Alabama on March 3, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. The letter explains the society's purpose and goals, while praising southern ideals. It then invites and requests Lee to become a member of the society.
        Alabama -- Perry County; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Stonewall Institute of Perry County, Alabama; Jefferson Davis Society
      - J. Longstreet to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-03; Longstreet, J. (Box 7A, Folder 43)
        This letter was written by J. Longstreet from New Orleans, Louisiana on March 3, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Longstreet writes to Lee informing him that he has inserted Lee's name as a one of the non-resident board of directors for the Great Southern and Western Life and Accident Insurance Company. He gives description of the company and its then-current assets. Included with the letter is a typed transcript.
        Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Great Southern & Western Accident & Life Insurance Co.
      - J. Johns Jr. Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-03; Johns, J., Jr. (Box 7A, Folder 43)
        This letter was written by J. Johns Jr. from Richmond, Virginia on March 3, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Johns writes to Lee that his letter accompanies another letter from Dr. Julius Doetsh. He explains that, upon his advice, Doetsh wishes to make a translation of Lee's work. He then vouches for Doetsh's credentials and character.
        Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Doetsh, Julius Edmund, M.D.
      - Dr. Julius Edmund Doetsh to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-03; Doetsh, Julius Edmund, M.D. (Box 7A, Folder 43)
        This letter was written by Dr. Julius Edmund Doetsh from Richmond, Virginia on March 3, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Doetsh introduces himself to Lee and makes an offer to translate Lee's in-progress memoirs into German for European publication. He explains that interest in Europe is high for such a publication, and explains the potential avenues for publication which he can take advantage of.
        Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Johns, J., Jr.
    - Correspondences, 1866-03-04-1866-03-08 (Box 7A, Folder 44)
      - W. H. McGuire to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-04; McGuire, W. H. (Box 7A, Folder 44)
        This letter was written by W. H. McGuire from Washington, DC on March 4, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. In her letter, McGuire relays to Lee her thanks for his assistance and relaying of the news of her husband's death.
      - Thomas H. Ellis to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-06; Ellis, Thomas Harding; James River and Kanawha Company (Richmond, Va.) (Box 7A, Folder 44)
        This letter was written by Thomas H. Ellis from Richmond, Virginia on March 6, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. In the letter, Ellis writes to inform Lee that the company's general assembly has voted to move forward with granting a French company an amended charter with contents that had been requested by the French company. He goes on to express his unease at working with the French, given bad relations and lack of resources following the Civil War. He then requests Lee write to him his opinions on the topics of the canal project, as well as peace relations abroad.
      - J. Speer Howarth to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-06; Howarth, J. Speer (Box 7A, Folder 44)
        This letter was written by J. Speer Howarth from Delaware County, Pennsylvania on March 6, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. In the letter, Howarth requests information on Washington College pertaining to its student population and the general atmosphere of the college.
      - J. Emanuel to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-07; Emanuel, J. (Box 7A, Folder 44)
        This letter was written by J. Emanuel on March 7, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Emanuel expresses interest in sending his son to Washington College and requests information on admission.
      - George M. Branner to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-07; Branner, George M. (Box 7A, Folder 44)
        This letter was written by George Michael Branner from Knoxville, Tennessee on March 7, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Branner writes the letter as an introduction to his son Hardy Bryan Branner and his friend Rudolph Bryan. He vouches for their character, and explains that all funds for their education are accommodated.
        Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Branner, Hardy Bryan; Bryan, Rudolph
      - E. C. Middleton to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-07; Middleton, E. C. (Box 7A, Folder 44)
        This letter was written by E. C. Middleton from Washington, DC on March 7, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. In the letter, Middleton introduces his agent, E. F. Lutz of Baltimore. Middleton then explains that his previous request of an oil painting of Lee had been rejected due to a lack of one existing. Middleton explains that Lutz will take notes of Lee's complexion and then, using a recent photograph by Mathew Brady, create an oil painting which he wishes Lee to sign.
        Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Brady, Mathew
      - J. W. Lapsley to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-07; Lapsley, John Whitfield, Col. (Box 7A, Folder 44)
        This letter was written by John W. Lapsley from Shelby County, Alabama on March 7, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. He writes to Lee introducing his son, John B. Lapsley who is attending Washington College. He goes into deep detail about his son's mannerisms and behavior, expressing hope that Lee's leadership will help to mold him appropriately.
        Lapsley, John B.; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward)
      - Benjamin B. Stith to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-07; Stith, Benjamin B. (Box 7A, Folder 44)
        This letter was written by Benjamin B. Stith from Bewleyville, Kentucky on March 7, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Stith writes that he wishes to send his son to a military academy, believing Lee to be the president of VMI. He asks Lee to send him information and his favor in accepting his son into the school.
      - Thomas E. McNeill to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-08; McNeill, Thomas E. (Box 7A, Folder 44)
        This letter was written by Thomas E. McNeill from Lynchburg, Virginia on March 8, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. McNeill writes to share with Lee the mission of the newly-formed Virginia Mining and Manufacturing Bureau. He asks Lee for his support and includes an attached circular pertaining to the organization.
        Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Virginia Mining and Manufacturing Bureau
    - Correspondences, 1866-03-09-1866-03-12 (Box 7A, Folder 45)
      - W. W. Early to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-09; Early, William W. (Box 7A, Folder 45)
        This letter was written by William W. Early from Hyattsville, Maryland on March 9, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Early requests from Lee a catalogue of classes for Washington College.
      - N. S. Ray to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-09; Ray, N. S. (Box 7A, Folder 45)
        This letter was written by N. S. Ray from Lebanon, Kentucky on March 9, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Ray asks in the letter for a catalogue of studies, as well as general information for Washington College. Ray explains that his son wishes to transfer from Centre College in Kentucky to Washington College.
        Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Washington College (Lexington, Va.); Centre College (Danville, Ky.: 1918- )
      - William Hunter to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-09; Hunter, William (Box 7A, Folder 45)
        This letter was written by William Hunter from Savannah, Georgia on March 9, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Hunter writes to Lee informing him that his three sons wish to attend Washington College. He describes the natures of his sons as well as their academic potential.
      - John Brown Baldwin to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-10 (Box 7A, Folder 45)
      - E. L. Hadden to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-10; Hadden, E. L. (Box 7A, Folder 45)
        Ths letter was written by E. L. Hadden from New York City on March 10, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Hadden writes to Lee informing him that he is returning to Lee a series of items recovered from the occupation of Arlington House at the onset of the Civil War.
      - J. L. Hocker to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-10; Hocker, J. L.; Periclean Society (Box 7A, Folder 45)
        This letter was written by J. L. Hocker on behalf of the Periclean Society of the University of Kentucky in Lexington, Kentucky on March 10, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. The letter is written to inform Lee that he has been elected as an honorary member of the society.
        University of Kentucky; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward)
      - C. Newton to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-10; Newton, C. (Box 7A, Folder 45)
        This letter was written by C. Newton from Louisiana State Seminary (later Louisiana State University) on March 10, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. The letter is written to inform Lee that a society has been formed at the school named the Lee Society, and that Lee has been elected an honorary member.
        Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Louisiana State University (Baton Rouge, La.); Lee Society
      - Francis H. Smith to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-12; Smith, Francis H., Colonel (Francis Henney) (Box 7A, Folder 45)
        This letter was written by VMI Superintendent Francis H. Smith on March 12, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Smith writes to inform Lee that a new VMI cadet, William F. Dancey, believes that the damage to VMI has resulted in the institution being unable to perform its purpose. He relays Dancey's desire to instead enroll in Washington College.
        Dancey, William F.; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Washington College (Lexington, Va.); Virginia Military Institute
      - Sam Barnett to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-12; Barnett, Sam (Box 7A, Folder 45)
        This letter was written by Sam Barnett from Washington, Georgia on March 12, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Barnett writes to Lee informing him that his ward, William H. Barnett, wishes to attended Washington College.
        Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Barnett, William H.
      - Rathmell Wilson to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-12; Wilson, Rathmell (Box 7A, Folder 45)
        This letter was written by Rathmell Wilson from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania on March 12, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Wilson writes the letter as a follow up to his previous correspondence with Lee regarding the donation of Thomas B. Wilson's library to Washington College. Wilson inquires whether the boxes of books arrived as planned. He also indicates that he wishes to donate further books in his possession to Washington College on the stipulation that the donated books be cared for, retain Thomas Wilson's book plate, and be called "the Wilson contribution to the Library of Washington College." Wilson additionally indicates that he has included a copy of Thomas Wilson's memoir in the donation.
    - Correspondences, 1866-03-13-1866-03-14 (Box 7A, Folder 46)
      - Lt. von Clausewitz to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-13; von Clausenwitz, Lt. (Box 7A, Folder 46)
        Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Pollard, Edward A.
      - J. Marshall Dent to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-13; Dent, John Marshall (Box 7A, Folder 46)
        This letter was written by J. Marshall Dent from Maryland Agricultural College on March 13, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. In the letter, Dent explains to Lee that the classes at Maryland Agricultural College are to be suspended by March 25. He requests information on Washington College and inquires of the possibility of enrolling late in the term.
        Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Washington College (Lexington, Va.); University of Maryland
      - C. G. Freuman to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-13; Freuman, C. G. (Box 7A, Folder 46)
        This letter was written by C. G. Freuman from Eminence, Kentucky on March 13, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Freuman requests that Lee send him a catalog for the "military institute" which Lee is head of, mistakenly assuming Lee is the head of Virginia Military Institute also in Lexington, VA.
        Virginia Military Institute; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward)
      - William H. Kinnon to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-13; Kinnon, William H. (Box 7A, Folder 46)
        This letter was written by William H. Kinnon from Tangipaho Station, Lousiana on March 13, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Kinnon writes to request information on costs of attendance for the sons of his five sisters.
      - C. B. Richardson to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-13; Richardson, C. B. (Box 7A, Folder 46)
        This letter was written by C. B. Richardson from New York City on March 13, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. In the letter, Richardson thanks Lee for his previous correspondence and expresses interest in sending Lee a series of documents and books to assist him.
      - S. D. Stuart to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-14; Stuart, S. D. (Box 7A, Folder 46)
        This letter was written by S. D. Stuart from Baltimore, Maryland on March 14, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Stuart writes on behalf of Mrs. James Robb, asking for a likeness of Lee, whom she greatly admires.
      - George William Green to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-14; Green, George William (Box 7A, Folder 46)
        This letter was written by George William Green from Shieldfield, Newcastle on Tyne, England.
        England -- Shieldfield; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward)
    - Correspondences, 1866-03-15 (Box 7A, Folder 47)
      - W. Scott Glore to Robert E. Lee, Glore, W. Scott (Box 7A, Folder 47)
        This letter was written by W. Scott Glore from Louisville, Kentucky on March 15, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Glore offers to pay for $1000 of the publication costs of Lee's in-progress written histories of his campaigns during the Civil War.
      - P. T. Moore to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-15; Moore, P. T. (Box 7A, Folder 47)
        This letter was written by P. T. Moore from Richmond, Virginia on March 15, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. In the letter, Moore explains that his friend from the British Parliament has requested an autographed photograph. Moore also explains that his other friend, Dr. Thomas Antisell, inquires about a potential agriculture or geology position at Washington College.
        Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Washington College (Lexington, Va.); Antisell, Thomas
      - Emma Willard to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-15; Willard, Emma (Box 7A, Folder 47)
        This letter was written by American educator Emma Willard on March 15, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. Willard introduces herself and explains that she is a writer of history and has followed Lee's career through the war. She expresses her wish to establish contact with various generals, including Lee, to record their views of experiences for an upcoming school history book on the topic.
        United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward)
      - American Publishing Company to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-15; American Publishing Company; Burr, J. B.; Scranton, S. S. (Box 7A, Folder 47)
        This letter was written by S. S. Scranton and J. B. Burr from the American Publishing Company from Hartford, Connecticut on March 15, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. They write to inquire on Lee's status in writing his history of the war, and continue to express interest in negotiating a publishing contract.
      - J. A. G. Williamson to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-15; Williamson, John A. G., 1844-1891 (Box 7A, Folder 47)
        This letter informs Robert E. Lee of his honorary membership to the Jackson Society, a literary society at the College of William and Mary. This was written by J. A. G. Williamson, the secretary of the society. The reverse shows that Robert E. Lee answered the letter on March 23rd, 1866.
        Literature--Societies, etc.; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; College of William & Mary; Jackson Society
      - Meade Woodson to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-15; Woodson, Meade, 1843-1882 (Box 7A, Folder 47)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from Meade Woodson of Fincastle, Botetourt County, VA. Woodson writes to Lee on behalf of a Ms. Hamilton who is considering sending her two sons to the institution. She wonders if there will military training at Washington College and if there's boarding for students available with Christian professors.
        Virginia -- Fincastle; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Washington College (Lexington, Va.)
    - Correspondences, 1866-03-16-1866-03-19 (Box 7A, Folder 48)
      - William C. Folkes to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-17; Folkes, William C., 1845-1890 (Box 7A, Folder 48)
        This is a letter from William C. Folkes to Robert E. Lee. He has sent a list of Battle Reports from the Confederate States of America (CSA). Along with the letter is a yellow piece of paper listing the battles recognized by the CSA.
        Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; American Civil War (United States: 1861-1865); United States--Confederate States of America
      - Fanny Bain to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-18; Bain, Fanny (Box 7A, Folder 48)
        This letter was sent to Robert E. Lee from "Fanny" Bain, a corresponding secretary of the Eunomian Literary Society. The society offers Lee honorary membership if he would send a letter of acceptance and make a contribution to the Literary Gems paper.
        Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Eunomian Literary Society; Masonic College (La Grange, Ky.)
      - Thomas T. Munford to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-18; Munford, Thomas Taylor, 1831-1916 (Box 7A, Folder 48)
        This letter was written by Thomas Munford for Robert E. Lee. HAving learned that R. E. Lee is planning to write a war memoir, Munford writes to Lee to correct information within the offical Confederate report of the cavalry battle at Aldie, Virginia in 1863.
        Battle of Aldie (Virginia: 1863); Cavalry; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Kilpatrick, Judson, 1836-1881
    - Correspondences, 1866-03-20-1866-03-22 (Box 7A, Folder 49)
    - Correspondences, 1866-03-26-1866-03-31 (Box 7A, Folder 50)
      - Abner Johnson Leavenworth to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-27; Leavenworth, Abner Johnson, Rev., 1803-1869 (Box 7A, Folder 50)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from Reverend Abner Johnson Leavenworth, writing as secretary of the Teachers' Association of Virginia. He asks Lee to address the organization's anniversary meeting in July 1866 about acceptance and education of Virginia's formerly enslaved people. Lee noted on the reverse of the Letter that he declined the invitation to speak.
        Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; The Teachers' Association of Virginia
      - Charles W. Cole to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-28; Cole, Charles W., 1842-1923 (Box 7A, Folder 50)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from Charles W. Cole. Originally this letter was given to Lee with two books, "Rollin's Belles Lettres" and "The Letters of Cicero" that came from his home in Arlington. This letter is an explanation for how Cole obtained them and why he is giving them back.
        Arlington House, the Robert E. Lee Memorial (Va.); Rollin's Belles Lettres; The Letters of Cicero; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; United States. Army. Ohio Infantry Regiment, 145th (1864)
      - John W. Fiwell, 1866-03-28 (Box 7A, Folder 50)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from John W. Fiwell. Fiwell asks for a circular of Washington College. Fiwell also mentions he is a wounded soldier from Company A of the Fourth Virginia Cavalry.
        Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870; Washington College (Lexington, Va.); Confederate States of America. Army. Virginia Cavalry Regiment, 4th
      - R. G. Williams to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-31 (Box 7A, Folder 50)
      - Edward Long Hedden to Robert E. Lee, 1866-03-30; Hedden, Edward Long, 1828-1893 (Box 7A, Folder 50)
        This letter to Robert E. Lee is from Edward Long Hedden. Hedden tells Lee he has received the engraving of Washington and gives his thanks.